For over 30 years,
A visionary artist,
coupled with a talented performer,
enjoyed great fame.
Serge Liffard embodied dance for his contemporaries and inspired several generations of choreographers.
This,
despite a dark period that tarnished its reputation.
Who is this creator and what secret lies behind this forgotten legend?
He was an important figure of the time.
like all movie stars.
Any concierge in Paris,
We were talking about Serge Liffard.
We knew who Serge Liffard was.
A truly exceptional character due to his vitality,
his creativity,
his enthusiasm,
The social side as well.
He was a completely unique individual.
For a generation,
Liffard was a...
The word is perhaps a bit of an exaggeration.
but like a god.
1913.
Nothing foreshadowed the impending catastrophe of the Great War.
Young Serge Liffard is 8 years old.
His passions are reading Pushkin's books and playing the piano.
Lying on the bank of the river that flows through the city of Kyiv,
Serge Liffard...
dream of a career as a musician.
His future seems glorious and all mapped out.
But then World War I broke out and shook the foundations of the Russian Empire.
Occupied by the Bolsheviks,
Ukraine is ravaged by a violent civil war.
Serge Liffard's grandfather is arrested by the secret police.
Her grandmother was burned alive during the looting of her house.
His family's property was seized and he suffered a hand injury caused by shrapnel.
He buries his dreams of a career as a pianist.
Serge Liffard's perfect world collapses,
and the teenager escapes into the forests of the kyiv region,
fleeing certain death.
Russia aims for a global revolution.
Young people his age must report to ships bound for Poland.
On board,
but torn apart by a love affair,
Serge pretends to be a deserter and decides to take the plunge.
in the middle of the night.
An idea, almost prophetic in nature, then began to germinate in his mind.
that he was spared in order to accomplish a mission.
This missed encounter with death acts as a resurrection.
his dive like a baptism.
It was in 1920 that Serge Liffard discovered dance,
while accompanying a friend to Bronislava Nijinska's studio,
sister of the famous star of the Russian ballets,
Václav Nijinsky.
It was love at first sight.
blown away by the beauty of the movements,
by the discipline of the dancers which contrasts with the political disorder of Ukraine.
The nature of his mission is revealed to him.
A day,
He will be a great dancer.
Nothing will matter to him anymore.
apart from dancing.
Destiny is set in motion.
The first step,
essential to the pursuit of its objective,
is to follow Nijinska's teachings.
But she is skeptical.
Despite his good looks and refined gestures,
Liffard is already 16 years old.
and his technique is far from matching his enthusiasm.
Initially refused,
under the pretext of being too old,
Serge Liffard will have to use his wits to attend the famous professor's lessons.
The summer of 1921 marked Nijinska's departure.
who is going to join the Ballets Russes troupe in Europe.
This famous company brings together the best elements of the Mariinsky Theatre in Saint Petersburg.
Performed on stages all over the world,
At that time, it embodied the cutting edge of modernity.
Russian art therefore dominated,
in particular the ball.
When
Brunieslava Nizhinskaya,
which was already developing within Diaghilev's company,
sent an invitation to his five best students.
There weren't any.
But after a few seconds,
Someone refused.
And his girlfriend...
Serge Liffard's dream is within reach.
But he lacks the money and travel documents to reach France.
It is through a method worthy of the greatest adventure films that he will manage to leave the country.
He has already worn this custom of the Queen of the Americans.
with all his pistols,
knowing,
I don't even know where he learned it.
maybe in Aboum,
that there was a herd of livestock at the station,
an officer of the
France. He came to the station,
He said,
I know your past,
I am from the GPU in Kyiv.
I know you are a white officer.
If you do not forward this to me at the Polish border,
I'll arrest you and put a gun on the ground.
He was
a 17-year-old boy.
At the age of 18,
the city,
at that time,
experienced a very intense artistic life in response to the horror of the First World War.
The Russian ballet company,
directed by the demanding Serge Diaghilev,
fills the halls with breathtaking shows.
It brought together all the artists,
whether they are painters,
whether they are composers,
writers,
in order to be able to create works of art.
In the lobby of the Hotel Continental,
Serge Liffard calms his anxiety by repeating a few movements.
Accompanied by the four dancers summoned by Nijinska,
He is indeed preparing to meet Serge Diaghilev.
The stakes are crucial.
If he wants to perform on stages all over the world,
He must be knighted by the emperor of the Russian ballets.
Right away,
this character who is a predator,
whose name is Diaghilev,
hires
18 years old.
But then,
How is it that such an average dancer can attract the attention of an impresario with infallible judgment?
The answer lies in Serge Liffard's most powerful asset,
his weapon of mass seduction,
his physique.
Liffard was handsome.
He had a splendid body.
He had extraordinary hands,
long,
thin.
He had,
There,
I believe everything.
He had gorgeous legs,
A magnificent foot.
He had that dark complexion that Liffard sometimes had.
her black hair,
He was extraordinary.
It was beauty itself.
Liffard,
with incredible charm.
A show will constitute a crucial step in the life of Serge Liffard.
The Blue Train,
It's a daring work.
avant-garde,
for which Henri Laurence painted the sets and Gabrielle Chanel took care of the costumes.
Liffard's athletic physique...
and showcased in the swimsuits of the famous designer.
Coco Chanel
to make Diaghilev's ear gasp,
Here it is.
trondanteur.
Diaghilev took him under his wing quite quickly,
Not right away, Serge Liffard.
Liffard saw the advantage that could undoubtedly be gained from being close to the autocratic director of the Ballets Russes,
Serge Diaghilev.
He was something of a favorite.
He was really the one who revealed it.
He shaped his taste.
He shaped her artistic education by taking her everywhere to museums in Italy.
Gaglielfe forced him to tell her what he had seen,
what he had thought of it,
what it had brought him,
etc.
Fantastic.
If the two friends also visit Italy so often,
This is because Liffard is studying under a new professor in Turin.
Determined to help his protégé develop his passion,
It was Diaghilev who introduced him to her during the summer of 1924.
His name,
Enrico Cecchetti.
His reputation,
that of a magician who elevates the dancers under his care to the rank of star.
Serge Lifar pulls a muscle in his left leg during a rehearsal.
On the rise, and about to break into their first major role,
His injury is a curse.
Serge Liffard continues his meteoric rise.
But according to Diaghilev,
The dancer's upturned nose catches the light poorly.
As a good mentor,
He will therefore offer his protégé one last gift.
a new appendix.
He had undergone facial surgery.
And he had,
after 1925,
after this extraordinarily successful operation,
a splendid face.
So Liffard had become beauty itself for the dancer.
Finished with a scalpel.
His physique is now a finished work of art.
which embodies an aesthetic ideal.
Serge Liffard...
will exert a certain fascination on his contemporaries and will be painted,
sculpted and described with emphasis by the press and the greatest artists of the 20th century.
Serge Liffard's fame grew and
He begins a social life in which he will quickly become the epicenter.
His friends include Paul Valéry,
Cocteau,
Chanel or Picasso.
They are among those who bring about artistic revolutions.
For the rising star,
The roles are multiplying.
Did his close relationship with Diaghilef contribute to his meteoric rise?
The charisma of IFAR,
the IFAR technique...
her beauty on stage which made that
Diaghilev gave him the major roles.
It's not solely because there was a private affinity between these two people.
SO
Liffard did not steal any of his roles.
He got them because he had the talent to do it.
At the very moment when Serge Liffard's fame is soaring,
A brilliant choreographer takes charge of the ballet troupe.
Georges Balanchine,
recognized today as a major figure in classical dance.
He will very quickly take advantage of the creature Serge Liffard.
Balanchine,
when he talks about Liffard,
with whom he didn't get along particularly well,
He had no connection with anyone,
The two men had two opposing personalities.
He is the first to say,
but I exploited him for his innate sense of the beauty of poses.
So he knew how to showcase his body.
Those who were a bit ironic would say of Liffard in the 1930s,
Mr.
Liffard is gradually moving towards full nudity,
because he was overexposing his body.
So the Ballets Russes had already undertaken this,
since dancers often danced with bare legs in the 1920s.
In 1929,
that's where
Liffard, under Diaghilev, will create his first choreography.
It is, in fact, a work by Stravinsky entitled
Fox.
The young prodigy's first creation is adapted from Russian folk tales.
It is performed in Paris and London and wins the public's approval.
Diaghilev died a few months later.
At his funeral in Venice,
Serge,
always to excess,
pretends to throw himself into his grave.
But a second event would propel the young choreographer's career,
Balanchine,
to whom the opera had just commissioned a ballet and struck down with severe pneumonia.
He was ill.
So he told management,
Take Serge Liffard in my place.
And Serge Liffard arrived.
He was very young.
He enters the opera house and will always be in awe.
kneeling before the opera house,
which, for him, is the greatest opera house in the world,
And that's his pride.
It took Serge Liffard only ten years to become,
at the age of 25,
choreographer and then ballet master in one of the world's greatest theaters,
the Opéra Garnier.
Serge Liffard made a pious vow to dedicate his life to dance,
which is a dusty body at this time.
He now has full powers.
to revolutionize it.
One of Liffard's contributions,
This is a way of bringing male dance back into the spotlight through the main roles, which are often male.
So that was the big evolution.
The dancer gained considerable importance from the moment Liffard arrived.
Serge Liffard changed the face of choreography and continued the work begun by Diaghilef, who made ballet the heart from which all the arts beat.
Music,
painting,
writing and dance,
Of course.
He brings the style of the Russian ballets,
that is to say, a more acrobatic style,
more gymnastic,
more angular.
Everything needs to be rethought.
because dance does not only suffer from a problem of obsolescence,
It is also stifled by a lack of representation.
That is to say, at the opera...
When IFAR arrives,
There is no evening entirely devoted to ballet.
At the time,
People come to see opera and ballet.
It was very exceptional to have an evening entirely devoted to ballet.
He will impose a weekly ballet evening starting in 1935.
After that,
He demanded two evenings during the week.
He did it on Wednesday and Friday.
After that,
We had the entire month of July,
which was ballet month.
But he had an ally,
a very favorable ally,
IFAR,
It's an economic crisis.
And dance is always cheaper than opera.
The situation is difficult during this period.
More and more French people are losing their jobs following the 1929 crisis.
Criticism is being raised, pointing to the excessive number of Russians within the Paris Opera.
Tensions are rising.
We still need to put ourselves back in the situation of the time.
First of all,
Liffard was not French.
He was stateless.
They made him feel it,
in Paris,
that he was a foreigner.
Let's not forget that in the 1930s,
There is the rise in power of the leagues,
the far right,
xenophobic,
etc.
And Liffard was the foreigner.
In this climate of hostility,
Liffard, however, manages to stage a show that will save his place at the opera.
This is Icarus,
a project that IFAR has been developing for a few years and for which Paul Lartre will design the sets.
Inspired by the myth,
It tells the story of a winged man who flies towards the sun.
THANKS.
The ballet reflects its era.
Civil aviation experienced a resounding boom during this period.
The press reports on the exploits of pilots like Charles Lindbergh,
who has just crossed the Atlantic,
and Saint-Exupéry,
who describes his flights to Africa in his novels.
Actually,
This ballet, created in 1936, is a monument of modernity.
of Master Icard, almost naked.
With accessories,
wings,
things like that,
It was truly revolutionary at the time.
Serge Liffard did this
He choreographed and composed the music himself.
He had a key and he tapped out all the rhythms.
And when he gave these rhythms to Honegger to set to music,
It was done using only percussion instruments.
That,
that was a revolution.
For him,
It is the choreographer who must first conceive their choreography in silence.
Then come the other arts.
There is a power struggle at play.
There is a question of precedence, in a way.
He wants to assert the primacy of dance,
always the primary element in his mind.
He once told me that man's first art,
It's the dance.
I was telling him,
Don't you think it's the music?
master ?
He told me,
No,
It's the dance.
the movement.
He convinces all his detractors in Icard by embodying a hero who dies and loses.
So I think it's quite pretty.
Liffard is a superstar.
And this idol status is characteristic of his modernity.
Egocentrism,
social evening,
overexposure of her body,
Serge Liffard was a celebrity before his time.
And its power of attraction is immediate.
He announces his plans.
Can we imagine today,
Release,
open three columns,
two,
three columns to a choreographer who is going to announce his future creation.
So he has a very high level of fame.
He loved being photographed,
He loved being with not only the political world but also the world of artists.
So obviously he was so adored,
So naturally, that inflates the character a bit.
When he mounted Prometheus,
He had a heated argument with the conductor.
because he wanted to add a chord.
So we told him no.
Beethoven's score must not be touched.
But he said,
Beethoven was famous,
But Serge Liffard too.
Apart from Icard,
Serge Liffard's innovations have received mixed reviews from critics.
While they are sometimes harsh,
However, the criticisms only have an artistic scope.
World War II will change everything.
and make it significantly more dangerous.
A period of uncertainty is being observed at the Paris Opera.
Following the general mobilization of September 3, 1939,
Many dancers are being requisitioned.
Luckily,
This mobilization does not concern artists of foreign nationality.
The Nansen passport,
delivered to Serge Liffard a few years earlier,
thus exempting the choreographer from any military service.
Serge Liffard continues his life as a dancer and choreographer and performs in Australia.
where he undertook a tour from January to March 1940.
It features the Spectre de la Rose,
The Lake of Signs and Icarus.
We had never seen a dancer like Liffard before,
also athletic,
wild and expressive.
There have been more than 25 encores during the biggest performances.
Serge Liffard is making headlines in the Australian press.
From Melbourne to Sydney,
He's all anyone is talking about.
1940,
Nazi Germany expands its empire in Europe.
Northern France and then Paris are occupied.
In the heart of the capital,
The pas de deux introduced by Liffard in his brooms are replaced by the rhythmic step of German boots.
Shortly after his return to France and the signing of the armistice on June 22, 1940,
The city of Paris will entrust Serge Liffard with a role of great importance.
To reopen the Garnier opera house to prevent the Germans from occupying the building.
Destroy the opera house and bring IFAR back to Berlin and build a dance school and ballet company in Berlin.
For IFAR,
A troubled period begins.
Forced to deal with the Germans who occupied the capital,
The choreographer first received Goebbels at the Paris Opera.
Then it was Hitler.
in person,
who then visits the opera house during a trip to the capital.
It is 6:30 in the morning when the Führer sets foot in the building.
Having been warned of the dictator's visit,
Liffard did not show up for work that morning.
But the public is unaware of this absence.
and thinks that the choreographer is fraternizing with the enemy.
Traumatized by the arrival of German troops,
The country's distrust of Serge Liffard is taking hold.
It's later,
in 1941,
that Serge Liffard truly meets the dictator.
The interview takes place in an office at the Führer's headquarters.
He had been summoned to Berlin by Hitler, who asked him to create a grand ballet.
a grand choreographic spectacle glorifying the Third Reich,
which he refused.
Accusations are starting to rain down in the capital.
Yet...
Serge Liffard's understanding with the enemy is not so obvious.
Obsessed with racist ideals,
The Germans have doubts about Serge Liffard's origins.
He was then quickly asked,
as with many other artists,
a certificate of Arianism.
Liffard was accused of being Jewish for a long time.
And then,
There was a faction of the SS who wanted him dead.
Because people said Liffard's face was Jewish,
etc.
He finally showed,
particularly through his brother's final year of high school
through physical and blood analyses,
etc.
He was able to get rid of the accusation of being Jewish.
Cleared of all suspicion,
Serge Liffard continues his mission at the Paris Opera.
Enjoying taking care of everything,
The young prodigy wears many hats.
He holds the positions of administrator,
but also as a concierge.
sweeper.
telephonist,
electrician,
dancer,
choreographer and of course ballet master.
He wanted a very quick death.
He died very quickly.
In one second,
It was stolen.
With the help of his great friend Jean Cocteau,
Liffard reintroduced danced poems to the opera stage.
Even though Cocteau found the choreographer somewhat superficial,
A certain originality of character brings these two great artists together.
During the war,
if they have to work together after curfew,
Liffard whistles the tune of dear chance under Cocteau's window.
In the space of 4 years,
Liffard composed 12 ballets,
including 6 original creations.
During these performances,
The rooms are half filled by soldiers or high-ranking officials of the German army.
When I returned to the opera,
The Germans were all in the orchestra.
It was a green carpet.
So we were obliged to dance there for the shows,
because they had actually asked for the theatre to be reopened for them.
After the shows,
Serge Liffard meets the cream of the German army in the capital's grand restaurants such as Maxim's or La Pérouse.
On the surface,
Liffard exhibits all the characteristics of a supporter of the Reich.
a man who regularly shares good meals with Nazis,
whom he also entertains during his shows.
He didn't necessarily have only friends,
So we immediately categorized him as a collaborator.
etc.
I think we've all been there,
Me,
at my own small level.
I was also a collaborator because I did all the shows.
Besides his high-society role that causes a stir,
Liffard presents another side of himself during the occupation.
more secret and more glorious.
It is that of a generous and empathetic man who participates in the war effort.
He began by offering his help to the dancers of the Paris Opera.
He had done a lot for the dancers,
even during the war,
where there were problems with dancers who were Israelites and whom he hid.
He has a male dancer's condition that prevented him from going on compulsory military service.
because he said at the time,
If you take them,
There are no more ballet performances.
It's very simple.
Serge Liffard continues to send large sums of money to various organizations.
in support of children who are victims of war or prisoners.
These sums are raised during countless galas.
in which Liffard participated during the war.
The dancer-choreographer puts his love of dance at the service of the French and thus responds to their needs for assistance.
He was eager to gain recognition for ballet.
His main goal was to make it known to the general public and explain that it is an art form.
that we need the equivalent of...
music,
comedy,
of writing,
literature.
Where one feels good,
That is the homeland.
And
Liffard was fine in a studio or on stage.
Drawn by the light of the lounges and reception rooms,
Serge Liffard flits about and makes friends with stars of his stature like Josephine Baker or with emblematic artists of the Third Reich like the sculptor Arnaud Brecker.
It was in a spirit of reaction that Serge Liffard created his most famous ballet in 1943.
"Suite in white".
Still performed today on the world's greatest stages,
"Suite in white"
is a real slap in the face to the Nazi regime.
irrefutable proof of the choreographer's commitment to elegance and freedom.
I remember very well what Serge Liffard said,
"A suit in white is a gem."
"Suit en blanc must be danced by the greatest dancers on the planet."
You don't really have a story,
It's a white broom.
but with many variations,
steps of 2,
steps of 3,
steps of 5,
And all of this is accurate to the millimeter.
And that's what makes this broom so powerful.
Suite en blanc is the quintessence of the neoclassical style introduced by the Ballets Russes.
This neoclassical style,
inextricably linked to the name of Serge Liffard,
stands out from the linear style of 19th-century ballet.
It incorporates angular shapes and broken joints,
very expressive.
And that,
That was, after all, his great choreographic idea.
where he exceeded the standards,
if you wish
academics.
The dancer's pointed position with his arm extended, his head like that, and his body slightly offset,
We immediately say it's the Lipharian style.
In sadness,
in a fit of anger,
joyfully.
From that position, we can move to all the feelings we might want to convey with that position.
That's the thing.
And it still looks really good.
The variation,
cigarettes
which is called in ballets,
She is alive.
This choreography is contemporary.
Very beautiful and complicated.
Suite en blanc was represented abroad during the occupation.
In the autumn of 1943,
November 27th and 28th,
Two performances with Liffard and other dancers from the opera took place at the Deutsch Opernaus in Berlin.
Peretti,
Chauviré and Schwartz.
It was on this occasion that Serge Liffard met the dictator for the second time.
He was impressed by the piercing gaze,
Hitler's piercing eyes when he stared at me.
He told me it was quite impressive.
This interview continues to tarnish Serge Liffard's reputation and his relationship with one of the Gestapo countesses.
Sonia Olinska,
bury it for good.
At a reception given by the countess,
He is indeed seen on her arm wearing the German uniform.
Liffard was not a cautious person.
I think he wasn't thinking very far ahead.
But from there,
He never was,
In my opinion, at least.
And based on the research I've done,
an active collaborator.
He was more of a passive collaborator who,
Yes,
was celebrated.
guest,
There.
Radio London,
a major institution of the resistance,
criticizes the choreographer's behavior.
The blow falls preemptively.
Serge Liffard was sentenced to death by the Free French and also by the Gestapo.
This perfectly illustrates the character's ambivalence at that time.
whom both sides believed to be the enemy.
They were there as conquerors.
What could they do?
Where could they go?
To Patride.
Above all, he wanted to save his ballet company and his building.
the opera.
1944.
The balance of power shifted in favor of Free France and its allies.
Paris was liberated in August and the hunt for collaborators began.
The purge begins.
Unlike others who are executed without trial,
Serge Liffard will benefit from a form of trial.
When we look at the purge committee of that time,
Today it would be a bit funny because it's really all the worst ballets.
the opera's clowns who were there and who decided the lives of others.
The verdict is in.
Liffard was banned for life from the opera and all state theaters.
by the purge committee.
A collective amnesia is in place.
These works are removed from the opera repertoire and the name of IFAR is removed from the posters of those that are still programmed.
From May 1945 onwards,
We are witnessing a battle over Liffard and his rehabilitation.
The leaflets,
Letters of support or condemnation are pouring in from all sides.
The two opposing sides that clashed during the sham trial of Serge Liffard are facing off again.
Yes,
Of course,
there were still lingering traces of that history of the war and then of the so-called collaboration.
So there were obviously still some reservations on the technical side.
We made this move.
Against the stagehands who didn't want him to return to the opera,
and we secured his return to the opera.
It was a big fight involving all the great dancers of the time.
It was a movement of passion for dance through Serge Lipin.
The famous choreographer will appear before the purge committee a second time.
The certificate,
dated June 19, 1946,
reveals that Hitler's reception at the opera was a fiction.
Following its re-examination...
The choreographer's sentence is reduced to just one year.
with retroactive effect.
November 1, 1945,
Serge Liffard is therefore free to resume his activities on French territory.
but on two conditions
that he does not dance and that he does not take a bow on stage at the end of the ballets.
All the stars and the entire top tier of the ballet,
They wanted their ballet master because their ballet master,
He created roles for them.
He fed them.
We were still in the big bowl,
in the old ballets.
We wanted something else.
We wanted Liffard to come back and do his choreography at the opera.
That was mainly it,
He wasn't the dancer we wanted.
He was the master.
Serge Liffard thus leaves the new Monte Carlo ballet which he had joined in 1945 and returns to the opera.
But only as a ballet master.
The rumor spread quickly through the building.
Something is there,
in the air.
The master is back.
He is my master.
He was our teacher.
And the word itself,
master,
It is no longer applied to anyone today.
When you see a person enter who has the bearing of a nobleman,
because he had a distinctive approach.
And to arrive with slicked-back hair,
blacks,
ebony,
like that,
in the studio,
to give the impression...
I don't know how to say it,
That's the aura he had when he arrived.
I,
witnessed the respect shown to Serge Leffard when he arrived in a rehearsal room.
This generosity.
He would arrive with his sheet music and he was a very, very, very musical person and everyone,
We were constantly energized.
In the rotunda where Liffard gives his dance classes,
The choreographer emphasizes the technique that he loves so much.
He likes complex figures.
virtuosity.
He also ensures that the performers become one with the music.
dancing in rhythm,
with regard to the one who deviates from it.
From time to time,
He would fly into rages.
I could hear it...
So he stamped his feet and he even said
" Shit !
"Shut up, damn it!"
he said.
He kept complaining about the dancers who weren't in sync with the music.
"Oh dear!"
he was saying swear words like "Shit,
Grandma!
"Go dance like a ghoul!"
he said.
because for him,
in ghoul,
That was truly the end of the artist.
In 1947,
Serge Liffard created the ballet Les Mirages.
a choreographic extravaganza in one act and two scenes.
He likes to tell a story.
Liffard,
He is a narrative choreographer.
Dance,
It was used to tell a story.
There.
And all of Liffard's ballets,
apart from Suite en Blanc,
These are stories he tells.
Inspired by surrealism and romance,
the ballet...
It tells the story of a man's relationship with his shadow.
Leaving this one behind to pursue dreams of love and glory in the abode of the Moon,
He finally joins her when the dreams appear in their true form.
that of Mirage.
It is 11:30 AM.
They went up to the Opera studio at midnight and worked until 2 a.m.
That,
It's the dancers' discipline.
It's the taste of the work of great dancers.
February 2, 1949,
Serge Liffard thus returns to the stage of the Opera as a dancer.
His return is first and foremost a symbol.
He was 44 years old at the time.
a difficult age to practice such a demanding discipline,
but flexibility,
technique and physical strength.
The last six years of his career would take the form of a fight.
Serge Liffard danced until the end of his abilities.
Maybe,
I would say,
too much.
And perhaps to leave behind images of him that weren't necessarily the person he was.
And we kept telling him how wonderful he was.
So he still believed he was wonderful.
And that's tragic because no matter how much we told him, "Master,
You shouldn't do that.
Master,
You shouldn't dance that.
He didn't understand.
On December 5, 1956,
Marc ceases to be a godfather on the national stage.
He plays the role of Albrecht in Giselle,
accompanied by Yvette Chauviré.
The performance is a triumph.
IFAR is called back twelve times on the opera stage.
The dancer is applauded.
his career,
his audacity,
his talent,
his dedication and longevity.
Some are even complaining about the somewhat late release.
I experienced the greatest moments of joy of my life here.
My entire creative life has passed within these walls.
And then,
naturally...
I experienced intense bursts of joy,
recognition
admiration.
And at the same time,
I had days of conspiracy.
Two years later,
after some outbursts which IFAR cloaks itself in pride,
He is also thanked by the opera house for his role as ballet master.
Thirty years in a house,
We get tired of people and eventually...
I mean,
But why are they still here?
I mean, it's...
And I think that's it.
after a while,
We'd had enough.
the management,
even the ballet masters,
Perhaps the dancers too,
to always have the same ballet master,
to always have the same person.
They wanted change.
They wanted something else.
It endured,
He stayed for a long time.
But I believe that at some point,
the French,
Unfortunately,
are not so conservative.
These are religious groups.
They eat everything.
And they were fed up with IFAR,
They wanted something else.
And then,
You had young choreographers coming onto the scene.
In France ?
The heirs,
at least,
choreographers who distinguished themselves after the Diffard period,
Nothing,
It's obviously Roland Petit and Maurice Béjart.
So Roland Petit doesn't accept it at all.
He said some very unpleasant things about Serge Diffard.
And yet it was Diffard who had initially brought him out.
as a dancer,
and on the other hand
Maurice Béjart always claimed it.
He inspired these two choreographers to pursue choreography.
I remember Roland saying that Liffard's choreography was outdated.
that it was no longer possible to see Liffard's choreographies,
but he drew a lot of inspiration from it.
Which Béjart revolutionized with his Rite of Spring,
by putting the dancers in tight-fitting academic costumes and all that,
It had already been done with Serge Liffard.
When
Liffard has left the Paris Opera.
forced,
because his contract was coming to an end,
For him, it was a truly extremely difficult period.
He said,
He finds it in the newspaper.
"I am guillotined."
Yes,
they cut off his head.
He could no longer be on stage,
He could no longer be behind the scenes.
He could no longer be in the Opera studios,
He was practically dead.
He had experienced fabulous triumphs and successes,
It must also be said.
in this theatre,
So he was very attached.
But it's true that he spent his life there.
He arrived at 8 a.m.
He left again at 8am/midnight.
He was losing his beloved home.
And therefore also,
He was losing the ability to practice his art.
So he took refuge in filmmaking,
He took refuge mainly in writing books.
and then he saw the young dancers.
And he helped them if he could.
While Liffard no longer holds as much interest for the dance world,
The newspapers continue to report on the actions and words of the character.
It was in 1958 that Serge Liffard's last and greatest stroke of media genius took place.
Serge Liffard,
determined to erase in blood a slap received in public at the Champs-Élysées theatre.
Drawn by the clash of weapons,
a crowd of journalists held the position of the ancient heart in this tragedy in the form of a pas de deux.
The origin of this duel,
a plagiarism of the ballet Suite en Blanc by the Marquis de Cuevas,
which produces it at the Théâtre des Champs-Elysées under the barely modified title
"Black and White".
The choreographer then confronts the marquis,
who slaps him.
Serge Liffard,
due to a lack of gloves,
He throws down his towel and demands retribution through a duel.
Cuevas was then 73 years old and Liffard 54.
We were coming down from rehearsal,
There was immediately a photographer or a journalist who was there.
“Mr. Liffard,
master,
Please ! "
Would you like to give us some information?
How does it work?
Then he looked at me,
he said,
Gilbert Maillère,
Go get the accessories.
So I went to the accessories section,
I would return with a sword or a foil.
So he struck a pose like this,
he said,
I'm going to pierce through.
Marquis, like a butterfly
telegraph,
marquise,
New York,
come and collect the corpse.
The moment was near.
Serge Liffard had equipped himself with a number of fetishes.
Leather gloves,
slippers and icons,
because a bad move can happen quickly.
The marquis said, "Now I'm going to skewer him," and he made this stab wound several centimeters long on his left arm.
Then he told me, Liffard, that the Marquis had a fit of tears and suddenly said, "I killed my son."
I killed the god of dance.
Serge Liffard received the care his condition required.
The Marquis de Cuevas sighed, thinking he had pierced his own son.
Thank goodness everything ends with entrechats.
Deprived of his passion,
Serge Liffard's mood will gradually deteriorate.
Even though he continues to work to promote the art of dance,
The enthusiasm is no longer the same.
30 years of glory have not been enough to quench his thirst for recognition and his need to express himself.
She is a woman who will provide Liffard with all the support he needs.
Liliane Hallefeld.
I believe that Liliane Hallefeld was very quickly seduced by this dark character,
Very beautiful.
still very famous
exciting,
keen.
She was his angel,
his guardian.
Lefarge was an emotional man.
under all social stressors,
like any creative person.
But she was probably his soul.
which gave him the power to find rest.
And Liliane first took him to Cannes to separate him from his Parisian environment.
and then afterwards,
many years later,
in Switzerland,
also partly to isolate him from the Parisian scene.
because Lilane wanted to have it for herself,
anyway.
And then he calls me one day out of the blue.
I am on the terrace of the Countess's villa.
Oh really?
And what do you do?
I'm sweeping the terrace because it needs sweeping.
And he told me, with great melancholy,
You see,
I am still the broomstick master.
Dancer and choreographer Serge Liffard died last night in Lausanne at the age of 81.
Minister François Léotard is paying tribute this evening to the last great choreographer to emerge from Diaghilev's Russian ballets.
And Mr.
Léotard wants the opera to maintain Liffard's work and present his best works.
We visited a tomb together in Egypt.
And we were together,
like that,
in front of the excavation of the dead body.
And then,
We were both sitting there,
and I said to him,
master,
your seat,
She is here.
He makes me,
Do you believe in life?
Do you believe that?
All at once,
He became a pharaoh.
Do you understand?
He had this side to him...